Tully Filmus Papers
Tully Filmus Papers
1928-1967
Filmus, Tully, 1908-1998
1 linear ft.
Correspondence (1928-1965), mostly incoming; printed material, including articles and reviews, clippings, and exhibition catalogs and invitations (1940s-1960s). Correspondents include ACA Galleries, American Artists' Congress, Emidio Angelo, Seena Donneson, Harry Freud, William Gropper, Harry Kurnitz, Solomon Lipp, Stephen Rogers Peck, Anton Refregier, Leopold Stokowski, and Paul Zucker.
149593
Biographical History
Russian American Jewish realist painter, portrait artist.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1928 to 1967, the Tully Filmus Papers comprises correspondence, artwork, and memorabilia of the Russian American realist painter (b. 1908). While reflecting the professional career of the Jewish artist, the collection also illuminates Filmus' involvement with the Jewish community, which was both the subject and audience for much of his work.
Incoming letters and miscellaneous printed material are incorporated into the Correspondence Subject Files (Boxes 1-2), which are arranged alphabetically. Correspondents include artists (Emidio Angelo, Henry Cooper, Francis Criss, Seena Donneson, Maxim Gottlieb, William Gropper, Elliot Offner, Anton Refregier); authors (Harry Kurnitz, Solomon Lipp, Stephen Peck, Paul Zucker); conductor Leopold Stokowski; patrons (Lester Avnet, Cyrus Brin, Thomas E. Dewey, Harry Freud, Max Fuchs, (Mrs.) Michael Halperin, Barbara Henry, Ted Lewis, Harry Merdinger, Myron Minskoff, Jack Nordiff, Ben and Zdenka Segall, Meyer Shein, Ian Starr, Boris Tarna); and theatrical personalities (Norman Bel Geddes, Arlene Francis). Organizational correspondence encompasses art galleries and museums (American Contemporary Art Gallery, Art Institute of Chicago, Carnegie Institute, Corcoran Gallery of Art, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, City Art Museum of St. Louis, Toledo Museum of Art, Whitney Museum of American Art); community and religious groups (Children's Astham Research Institute, Community Synagogue, New York Psychoanalytic Institute, North Shore Community Art Center, Temple Beth-el of Great Neck, Women's American Organization for Rehabilitation Through Training) educational institutions (American Artists School, Cooper Union, Educational Alliance, Massachusetts Institute of Technology) and professional organizations (American Academy of Arts and Letters, American Artists' Congress, Artists Equity Association, Audubon Artists).
Artwork includes technical notes on painting and a North Shore Community Arts Center program cover featuring a Filmus drawing of Charles Dickens. Articles and reviews, clippings, exhibition catalogs and invitations (1940s-1960s), and various other printed materials constitute Memorabilia.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Angelo, 1903-; Donneson, Seena.; Filmus, Tully, 1908-1998.; Freud, Harry, 1909-1968.; Gropper, William, 1897-1977.; Kurnitz, Harry.; Lipp, Solomon.; Peck, Stephen Rogers, 1912-; Refregier, Anton, 1905-; Stokowski, Leopold, 1882-1977.; Zucker, Paul, 1889-1971.; ACA Galleries.; American Artists' Congress.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Jewish artists -- United States.; Jews, American.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Portrait painters -- United States.; Portrait painting -- United States -- 20th century.; Realism in art.; Russian Americans.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Invitations.; Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Family Correspondence
  - Family, 1947-1965; undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence-Subject Files
  - ACA Galleries, 1961-1965; undated (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1965; undated (Box 1)
  - American Artists' Congress, Inc., 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - American Artists School, 1937-1940 (Box 1)
  - American Contemporary Art Gallery, See ACA Galleries
  - American Federation of Arts, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - American Fund for Israel Institutions, 1948-1952 (Box 1)
  - American Fund for Palestinian Institutions, See American Fund for Israel Institutions
  - Angelo, Emidio, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1940-1942; undated (Box 1)
  - Artists Equity Association, Inc., 1950-1965 (Box 1)
  - Audubon Artists, 1944-1948 (Box 1)
  - Avnet, Lester, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Brin, Cyrus, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1941-1948 (Box 1)
  - Children's Asthma Research Institute, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Community Synagogue, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Cooper, Henry and Betty, 1942-1965; undated (Box 1)
  - Cooper Union Art Schools, See Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art
  - Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, 1938-1948 (Box 1)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1941; undated (Box 1)
  - Criss, Francis, undated (Box 1)
  - Dewey, Thomas E., 1955 (Box 1)
  - Donneson, Seena, undated (Box 1)
  - Educational Alliance, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Francis, Arlene, undated (Box 1)
  - Freud, Harry, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Fuchs, Max, 1943-1945; undated (Box 1)
  - Geddes, Norman Bel, undated (Box 1)
  - Goodman, Bee, See Lewis, Ted
  - Goodman, Philip, See Jewish Book Council of America
  - Gottlieb, Maxim B., undated (Box 1)
  - Gropper, William and Sophie, 1947-1962; undated (Box 1)
  - Halperin, Michael (Mrs.), undated (Box 1)
  - Henry, Barbara W., 1944 (Box 1)
  - Javits, Jacob K., 1965 (Box 1)
  - Jewish Book Council of America, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Kurnitz, Harry, undated (Box 1)
  - Lewis, Ted, 1948; undated (Box 1)
  - Lipp, Solomon, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology. School of Industrial Management. Schell Room Committee, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Merdinger, Harry, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Minskoff, Myron A., 1964 (Box 1)
  - New York Psychoanalytic Institute, 1959-1963 (Box 1)
  - Nodiff, Jack, 1954 (Box 1)
  - North Shore Art Festival, 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - North Shore Child Guidance Association, See North Shore Art Festival
  - North Shore Community Art Center, 1958-1965 (Box 1)
  - Offner, Elliot, undated (Box 1)
  - Peck, Stephen R., 1941 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1928-1964 (Box 1)
  - Progressive Citizens of America, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Quaison-Sackey, Alex, 1963-1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Refregier, Anton, 1961 (Box 1)
  - [City Art Museum of] St. Louis, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Schell Room Committee, See Massachusetts Institute of Technology. School of Industrial Management. Schell Room Committee
  - Segall, Ben and Zdenka, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Shein, Meyer (Mrs.), 1941 (Box 1)
  - Shelley Graphics, Ltd., 1963 (Box 1)
    See also World Publishing Company
  - Soyer, Moses, See Educational Alliance
  - Starr, Ian and Susy, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Stokowski, Leopold, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Taft Youth and Adult Center, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Tarna, Boris M. and Lore, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Temple Beth-el of Great Neck, 1956-1965 (Box 1)
  - Toledo Museum of Art, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Weiss, David and Stymean, 1963; undated (Box 1)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1940-1951; undated (Box 1)
  - Women's American Organization for Rehabilitation Through Training, See Women's American ORT
  - Women's American ORT, 1959-1964; undated (Box 1)
  - World Publishing Company, 1963; undated (Box 1)
    See also Shelley Graphics, Ltd.
  - Zucker, Paul, 1941 (Box 1)
  - A-Z, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Unidentified (Box 2)
- Artwork
  - Notes on painting (technical) (Box 2)
  - Reproduction (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles, reviews, 1940-1965 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1940-1965; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Exhibition catalogs, invitations, 1940s-1960s; undated; 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Memberships, awards (Box 2)
  - Teaching-related, 1934; 1961-1965 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 items (Box 2)